[Music]
welcome to this session on what's new in
Al for this release my name is stepen
Belo and I'm going to take you through
some of the changes to the language
that's been made in business Central
2025 release Wave
1 let's start with something you might
remember from the previous releases the
move of fields and tables in your
applications in this release we have
opened up for the use of the move to and
move from properties on tables and
Fields with this you can move your
fields and your tables between
applications I recommend that you watch
the session on what's new in appsource
apps and isvs let's move on to something
else that you might already know the
resources resources in apps has been
opened up for everyone to use now we did
a few additions let's talk about it well
let's start with the first things first
you need to specify a resource root
folder in order to start using resources
so here in my app
Json I have specified a resources route
called my resources in my resources I've
put some files some configuration files
some text files and a picture that I can
use in my
application if I want to use the
resource in my application I need to
reference it by its full name in this
case I would use the full name from the
resource root folder config and then the
actual config pick file and here the
facts and then the actual file for this
release we added a function that allows
you to list resources like I'm doing
here where I'm listing the resources in
the SpaceX folder and only the resources
that are of type
txt the filtering here is a simple
pattern matching but still very powerful
to allow you to find a lot of resources
in for example a
folder for this release we also made it
easier for you to get the content out of
the resources in this case here I'm
using the get Resource as text to get
the text of the resource this way I do
not need to handle the stream
itself the default encoding for text in
a resource is MS DOS so you need to make
sure that you specify the encoding to
get the right
output we also made it easy for you to
get a Json object from a resource with
the get resource as Json function I can
get the resource as a Json object again
here I want to make sure that I
understand the encoding and specify the
one that I need for my
resource of course you can still use the
get resource and get the stream out of
it again if you want to get text from
the resource uh from that resource
stream you should specify the encoding
of that text in this release we also
Revisited the limitations of the
resources so let's take a look at
that the new limits for a single
resource is 16
mbes the maximum size of all the
resources in the entire app is 250
megabytes the maximum size of the
resource name that is the name of the
resource from the resource route until
the end of the file name is 250
characters and the maximum number of
resources per an app is 250 six
resources it's quite a lot of
resources the compiler will hint you on
some of the prohibited file extensions
but in the end the server you're
deploying the application to is the one
determining what is allowed to be used
on that server and of course when you
upload an application to the cloud it
will be scanned for
malware okay let's get move on to
something new for Pages or page
extensions in this case we have added
the ability to override the card page ID
this can be especially helpful for the
scenarios where there is no card page ID
to begin with OR that you have a
scenario where the card page ID needs to
be
updated in this release we also added a
new page type it's called the user
control host the user control host page
type allows you to create a page that
has a full user control inside the page
and nothing
else this this also means that you need
to specify only one user
control and you cannot have actions on
that user control such a fulls screen
user control could be used for powerbi
reports could be used for a browser like
I do here we show some health content or
any other scenario where you want to
have a full screen user control there
are a few limitations that we are still
working on but go ahead and try it out
to see if it fits your needs and give us
some feedback
moving on to
reports for reports we added tool tips
the tool tips will give you insight into
what this report is about and if you add
an action on a page that points to a
report using the Run object property
then this tool tip will be inherited you
can of course still override it in the
page action but by default the tool tip
will be inherited and you don't need to
copy it to the
page another property that was added
here
is the Excel layout multiple data sheets
this new property will allow you to
split your data set or split the data
items in your data set into multiple
sheets in Excel so instead of having one
data table in a sheet that has all the
values from all your data items you can
now have each data item in a separate
sheet this could be related data it
could be Dimensions it could be a lot of
things that will make it much easier to
to search and find in Excel if they're
split up in separate data tables I
recommend watching the what's new in
reporting for developers session in
order for you to get a deep detail of
this
functionality the property itself can be
overwritten in the report layouts so you
can use the same data set both in
multiple sheets and in one sheet
depending on your
needs for reports we also enable you
to OB solete layouts here you can see
we've obsoleted a layout that does not
use the Excel layout multiple data
sheets property so the new report we
created will use separate sheets for
each data
item for the reports we also added a few
new triggers the on pre-rendering and
the on post report allowing you for even
more control of the report
generation and in the report you can now
access the target format so what are we
generating here in order for you to
actually change the code based on the
target format talking about
reports maybe you want to preview a
report in this release we added the
ability to view from stream the view
from stream will show a preview of the
document in the client without the user
having to download it and then open it
afterwards if you're on premised you
could also preview a specific path if
needed if you want to send a URL to some
other user you can now also include the
layout in that
URL the current supported layouts that
we can generate with the get URL
function is list tall tiles tiles and
Analysis let's move on to something
completely
different you can now use negative
numbers in in the increment string
function sometimes you just need to go a
little bit back and talking about going
back sometimes you need to troubleshoot
who called you and how did you get to
where you are so we added the call stack
function that allows you to get the
current callstack without throwing an
exception
first we also improved readability by
introducing the keyword
continue this is actually a BC ideas
that has now been implemented and can
help you make the loops more readable by
allowing you to skip the current
iteration of the loop and go to the next
one anywhere within the loop this can
make the code more readable and make the
easier to understand when and when
you're not moving on in the
loop we've worked a lot with strings in
this release and Jason so here we've
added the ability to create a multi-line
string
the only thing you need to do is put an
at and then the start of the string and
then everything that is inside that
string until the end of the single quote
will be the entirety of the string that
includes all new lines and it makes
things like this snippet much easier to
read we've also added the ability to
call two
text on simple
types the two text method without any
parameters will give you the same value
as the format if you specify the
invariant then it will give you the same
value as format
09 for more advanced functionality on
formatting and getting to that format
that you need you still need to use the
format
function for the Json object we made it
easier for you to get to the data in
there everything in the Json object is
text but sometimes it's nice to get the
right data type out of that text right
at the
beginning so here you can see I've use
the get text method to get the
destination this is much simpler than
having to go through a Json token and
adjacent value in order to get that
text however it does have some
limitations I don't know if the property
is there or not and that would cause an
exception if it's not there
to support that we've added an ability
for you to return the default value of
that type that you
want in order for you to test if the
property is there if you want more
functionality on testing what's inside
the Json document you still need to use
the Json token and Json
value let's try and experiment just a
little bit to see what else is in
there so here you can see we made it
quite easy to get an array get an
integer Boolean bite cha and so forth
this makes working with Json objects
much
easier okay we also added the ability to
write and read yaml in the Json object
while yamon and Json is not the same it
looks very similar it's just more
readable and sometimes this is used for
configuration files and other scenarios
where user may need to go and
edit the read from and write to yaml
functionality has been
backported to runtime version
143 so if you haven't started already
then even the bc25 versions now support
the read and write from
yl let's look at a couple of properties
that we actually scrolled through just a
second ago if we go to the report and we
look at our request page we can see a
few properties here called about title
and about text these were introduced
some time ago to help uh users
understand what this object is about and
give some teaching tips to give the user
the best possible start of using the
page when we look at our Ro Explorer the
only thing we have available in the role
Explorer experience is the caption and
the tool tip in this release we made it
uh easy to inherit the about title and
about text so now you can see the about
title and about text in the role
Explorer from the report without having
to specify it on the action
itself if we go back
to our presentation here we can actually
see an example of such so here I have my
uh role Center and I've added some
actions there as we saw I see the I icon
and if I click that I will now see the
about text and about title giving me
great insights into how to use this
report page and
functionality there are many other
examples in the product on how to use
this and you can use of course the
standard formatting for teaching tips
finally let's look at tests in this
release we added the ability for you to
catch an outbound
request we added the Handler HTTP client
Handler for you to specify on your test
functions and that will allow you to
intercept the call to an outbound
service you can use this to avoid having
to call an external service and I
recommend watching the mocking session
on how to use this in more details
finally we added the ability to specify
that you do not want want to use the
server certificate validation we do not
recommend you using this in production
but for test purposes with connecting to
local Services self- signed certificates
and so on this can be very
useful it's super simple you take your
HTP client and you set the use server
certification validation to false and
you're
off that's it for me in this session
there are many other changes to the a
language extension you can always go to
the change lock on the AL language
extension page in your vs code to see
all the details that have been added to
this release and I encourage everyone to
go try out the pre-release for any
upcoming versions and all the changes
that we will do there thank you very
much